Guide to the Daughters of the Cincinnati Records 1894-1998 MS 3031
New-York Historical Society
Daughters of the Cincinnati records
1894-1998
New-York Historical Society
Daughters of the Cincinnati
MS 3031
21 Linear feet (25 boxes)
The Daughters of the Cincinnati records contain a variety of documents concerning the formation of the hereditary lineage organization and its activities. The collection contains minutes, yearbooks, annual reports, correspondence, financial and organizational records, clipping scrapbooks, invitations, and photographic materials.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Daughters of the Cincinnati, 2017
Arrangement
The Daughters of the Cincinnati Records are organized in four series. Within those series, the materials are divided into subseries and arranged chronologically.
Series I: Minutes and Annual Reports
Series II: Organizational Records
Series III: Scrapbooks and Ephemera
Series IV: Photographs
Historical Note
The Daughters of the Cincinnati is a hereditary lineage organization founded in 1894 by female descendants of American Revolutionary War officers. The organization's stated purpose is to advance and encourage the study of the history of the Revolution, and its main philanthropic aim is to provide college scholarships to the daughters of current military officers. To be eligible for membership, applicants must prove that they are descended from an original member of the Society of Cincinnati, or a Revolutionary War officer who met the requirements for membership.
The Daughters of the Cincinnati was incorporated in New York State on Dec. 27, 1894, 111 years after the founding of the Society of the Cincinnati, an organization which does not admit female members. The Society of the Cincinnati was founded in 1783 by officers of the Continental Army and their French counterparts who served together in the American Revolution. The organization took its name from the ancient Roman hero Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus, whom they considered the embodiment of civic virtue. The primary aims of the Society of Cincinnati were to perpetuate the memory of the Revolutionary War and promote the ideals of the Revolution, and to provide support for members and their families. In order to perpetuate their organization and its aims, the founders made membership hereditary. Hereditary members of the Society of the Cincinnati are qualified male descendants of commissioned officers who served in the Continental Army or Navy.
Related Materials
The library holds a copy of the Daughters of Cincinnati 1979 publication A Salute to Courage: the American Revolution as seen throught the wartime writings of officers of the Continental Army and Navy. It also holds copies of the Constitution and by-laws, as well as some volumes of the organization's yearbooks.
Scope and Contents
The Daughters of the Cincinnati records contain a variety of documents concerning the formation and development of the organization and its activities. The collection contains minutes, yearbooks, annual reports, correspondence, financial and organizational records, clipping scrapbooks, invitations, and photographic materials.
Women -- Societies and clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Daughters of the Cincinnati
- Series I: Minutes and Annual Reports, 1895-1998
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes the minutes of the monthly Board of Managers meetings, as well as annual general meetings, from 1895 through 1988, and 1998. The minutes contain discussions of the current business of the organization, reports of various committees, and upcoming elections. These transcripts also provide details about the death of members, issues related to membership requirements and applications, and planning for events, trips, and fundraising efforts for scholarships. Minutes are divided into two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. is comprised of typescripts that are housed in their original binders. The date range is 1895 to 1964.
  Subseries I.B. consists of one handwritten minute book documenting meetings from 1904-1911, as well as folders of minutes arranged chronologically. The date range is 1895-1998, and the series includes a mix of handwritten minutes, original typed minutes and photocopies.
  This series also contains the Daughters of the Cincinnati annual reports and yearbooks for the years 1898, 1899, 1901, 1908, 1910-11, 1914, 1915, 1916, 1917, 1940, and 1969. These reports include financial information, the names of officers, directors and executive staff, and a narrative description of the work performed in that year. The library has a separate collection of Daughters of the Cincinnati yearbooks, including some volumes not found within this collection. These can be requested through the library's online catalogue.
  - Subseries I.A. Minutes in binders, 1895-1964
    This subseries is comprised of typescripts of meeting minutes that are housed in their original binders. The date range is 1895 to 1964.The minutes contain discussions of the current business of the organization, reports of various committees, and upcoming elections. These transcripts also provide details about the death of members, issues related to membership requirements and applications, and planning for events, trips, and fundraising efforts for scholarships.
    - Minutes (bound), 1895-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minutes (bound), 1900-1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Minutes (bound), 1911-1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Minutes (bound), 1911-1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Minutes (bound), 1918-1920 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes (bound), 1921-1922 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - Minutes (bound), 1921-1922 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Minutes (bound), 1923-1924 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - Minutes (bound), 1925-1930 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - Minutes (bound), 1931-1935 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Minutes (bound), 1936-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Minutes (bound), 1941-1944 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Minutes (bound), 1945-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Minutes (bound), 1948-1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    - Minutes (bound), 1955-1959 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    - Minutes (bound), 1960-1964 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Subseries I.B. Minutes, 1895-1998
    This subseries consists of one handwritten minute book documenting meetings from 1904-1911, as well as folders of minutes arranged chronologically. The date range is 1895-1998, and the series includes a mix of handwritten minutes, original typed minutes and photocopies. The minutes contain discussions of the current business of the organization, reports of various committees, and upcoming elections. These transcripts also provide details about the death of members, issues related to membership requirements and applications, and planning for events, trips, and fundraising efforts for scholarships.
    - Minutes, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1897-1898 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    - Minute book (handwritten), 1904-1911 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1911 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1912 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1914-1916 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 1917 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1918 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1919 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1920 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1921 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1922 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1923 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 1924 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1925 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, 1926 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1971 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1972 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1973 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1974 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1975 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1976 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 1977 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1978 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, 1979 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1980 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, 1981 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, 1982 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 1983 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    - Minutes, 1984 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    - Minutes, 1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, 1986 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, 1987 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
    - Minutes, 1988 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 18)
    - Minutes, 1998 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 19)
  - Subseries I.C. Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1898-1969
    This series contains the Daughters of the Cincinnati annual reports and yearbooks for the years 1898, 1899, 1901, 1908, 1910-11, 1914, 1915, 1916, 1917, 1940, and 1969. These reports include financial information, the names of officers, directors and executive staff, and a narrative description of the work performed in that year.
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1898 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1899 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1901 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1908 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1910-1911 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1914 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1915 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1916 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1917 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1940 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10)
    - Yearbooks and Annual Reports, 1969 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11)
- Series II: Organizational Records, 1894-1995
  This series includes general organizational records such the application for incorporation, the constitution and by-laws, requirements for membership, histories, registrar book and member lists, scholarship record books, correspondence, and material related to the 1979 book A Salute to Courage. It also includes financial records such as bequests to the organization, deeds and mortgages, and insurance policies.
  - Subseries II.A. General organizational records, 1894-1995
    This subseries includes general organizational records such the application for incorporation, the constitution and by-laws, requirements for membership, histories, registrar book and member lists, scholarship record books, correspondence, and material related to the 1979 book A Salute to Courage.
    - Application for incorporation, 1894 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1901 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1925, 1932 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1942,1948,1949 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1956,1964 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1970 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1981 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
    - Constitution and By-laws, proposed revisions, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
    - Constitution and By-laws, proposed revisions, 1921-1977 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
    - Constitution and By-laws, proposed revisions, 1979-1988 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1895-1925 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1994 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
    - Histories, ca. 1920-1980 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3)
    - Member lists, 1905-1995 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4)
    - Officer duties, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5)
    - Qualifications for membership, 1946-1980 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
    - Registrar record book, 1895-1981 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 11)
    - Scholarship record book - General Robert Anderson scholarship, 1923-1956 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 12)
    - Scholarship record book - John Chester scholarship, 1926-1955 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 13)
    - Scholarship record book - George Washington and Thomas Jefferson scholarships, 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 14)
    - Material related to the book A Salute to Courage., 1979 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7)
    - Material related to the Society of the Cincinnati, 1977 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8)
    - Material related to the Conference of Patriotic and Historical Societies, 1958 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
  - Subseries II.B. Financial records, 1924-1989
    This subseries contains financial records such as bequests to the organization, deeds and mortgages, and insurance policies.
    - Bequests and wills, general, 1952-1981 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
    - Bequests and wills, Jaffray Estate, 1949-1951 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
    - Bequests and wills, Starr Estate, 1973-1981 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
    - Bequests and wills, Wells Estate, 1924-1952 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
    - Deeds and mortgages, 1928-1946 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
    - Insurance policies, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
    - Insurance policies, 1976 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 7)
    - Insurance policies, 1984-1987 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 8)
    - Misc. financial documents, 1973-1989 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9)
- Series III: Scrapbooks and Ephemera
  This series contains invitations and material related to events organized by the Daughters of the Cincinnati, such as trips, cocktail parties, and dinners, in addition to clippings scrapbooks documenting these events.
  - Subseries III.A. Ephemera, 1915-1995
    This series contains invitations and material related to events organized by the Daughters of the Cincinnati, such as trips, cocktail parties, and dinners. It includes ephemera from the 75th Anniversary Dinner in 1970, at which Shirley Temple Black was presented with the first Daughters of the Cincinnati Award.
    - Events and invitations, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
    - Events and invitations, 1915-1919 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
    - Events and invitations, 1920-1925 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3)
    - Events and invitations, 1930-1938 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4)
    - Events and invitations, 1940-1948 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 5)
    - Events and invitations, 1950-1959 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
    - Events and invitations, 1960-1965 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
    - Events and invitations, 1966-1969 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8)
    - Events and invitations - 75th Anniversary (2 folders), 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 9-10)
    - Events and invitations, 1970 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 11)
    - Events and invitations, 1971 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1)
    - Events and invitations, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 2)
    - Events and invitations, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 3)
    - Events and invitations, 1978 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 4)
    - Events and invitations, 1979 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 5)
    - Events and invitations, 1980 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 6)
    - Events and invitations, 1981 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7)
    - Events and invitations, 1982 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8)
    - Events and invitations, 1983 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 9)
    - Events and invitations, 1984 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 10)
    - Events and invitations, 1985 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
    - Events and invitations, 1986 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 12)
    - Events and invitations, 1987 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 13)
    - Events and invitations, 1988 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 14)
    - Events and invitations, 1989 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 15)
    - Events and invitations, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 16)
    - Events and invitations, 1993-1995 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 17)
    - Stationery, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 18)
  - Subseries III.B. Scrapbooks, 1915-1990
    This subseries contains clippings scrapbooks related to events organized by the Daughters of the Cincinnati, including cocktail parties, dinners, trips to historic sites. One scrapbook documents the publication of the book A Salute to Courage in 1979.
    - Scrapbook, 1915-1922 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1928-1930 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1932-1936 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1936-1939 (Offsite-box 16, Volume 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1940-1948 (Offsite-box 17, Volume 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1948-1952 (Offsite-box 18, Volume 6)
    - Scrapbook, 1954-1957 (Offsite-box 19, Volume 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1956-1972 (Offsite-box 19, Volume 8)
    - Scrapbook - A Salute to Courage, 1979 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 9)
    - Scrapbook, 1987-1990 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 10)
- Series IV: Photographs, ca.1970s-1995
  This series contains snapshots of various events hosted by the Daughters of the Cincinnati, including celebrations, trips and ceremonies from the 1970s through 1990s. The series contains one box of loose photographs, arranged chronologically. Most are dated, and some are captioned. The 1980 Ball with the Sons of the Revolution is particularly well documented. The series also includes two albums which document the organization's Centennial celebrations held in 1994-1995. Handwritten captions identify most of the people pictured in the albums.
  - Album - Centennial celebration (2 volumes), 1994-1995 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 15-16)
  - Photographs, ca. 1970s (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1976-1978 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1979 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (4 folders), 1980 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 4-7)
  - Photographs, 1982-1987 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, ca. 1980s (Offsite-box 25, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1991 Feb. (Offsite-box 25, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1991 Apr. (Offsite-box 25, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 1991 Apr.-Dec. (Offsite-box 25, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, undated (Offsite-box 25, Folder 13)